British Columbia Honey Producers Association fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
British Columbia Honey Producers Association fonds
1923 - 2005
F-147
Q103514769
3.17 m of textual records 3 photographs 1 audio cassette
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of the records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by Mark Winston, Professor, SFU Department of Biological Sciences (March 2001); the SFU Department of Biological Sciences (March 2001); and the SFU Faculty of Science (April 2001).
British Columbia Honey Producers Association
The British Columbia Honey Producers' Association (BCHPA) was founded in 1920 and continues as an active organization. Its functions are to promote beekeeping as a profitable activity, promote and assist in the marketing of produce and purchase of supplies, support apicultural research and education, and disseminate information about beekeeping and best practices to both Association members and the general public. BCHPA membership includes both commercial honey producers and hobbyists.
The BCHPA was formed as a result of a split within the Beekeepers Association of British Columbia, founded four years earlier in 1916. The disagreements related to the outbreak of a bee disease in 1916 and the requirement of registration for all beekeepers under the provincial government's revised Foul Brood Act. When the BCHPA broke away in 1920 it established two Divisions – Fraser Valley and Kootenay; in 1925 the Vancouver Island Beekeepers' Association joined as a third Division. The two provincial associations merged in 1931, with the older organization entering the BCHPA as the Greater Vancouver Division. Membership in the BCHPA peaked in 1978 with 1,290 members and 32 Divisions.
The BCHPA is organized into geographically based Divisions. A Central Executive acts as a coordinating body for Association-wide business, and is assisted by various standing and ad hoc committees. Divisions are headed by their own Executives and are responsible for holding divisional meetings, publishing newsletters, collecting membership fees, operating educational programs, acting as a purchasing cooperative for supplies and medications, advising the Central Executive and preparing resolutions for the BCHPA annual general meeting. The Central Executive is headed by an elected President and consists of officers elected at the annual meeting and appointed regional representatives. It functions primarily as a liaison body between the various Divisions and between the Association as a whole and the provincial Ministry, the BC Federation of Agriculture and the Canadian Honey Council. It is also responsible for producing the Association's newsletter.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of the organization.The title is based on the contents of the fonds.
The fonds comprises records made or received in the course of administering the BCHPA's central and divisional organizations and carrying out their functions and programs. Most of the records originated with the Central Executive. Activities documented include board, committee and general members' meetings; correspondence of BCHPA officers; management of Association finances; evolution of the BCHPA constitution, by-laws and organizational structure; advice to governments and intervention in public policy debates relating to apiculture; production of the Association's newsletter; development of beekeeping educational programs and seminars; and participation in markets, exhibits and fairs. Records include constitution and by-laws; meeting agendas, minutes and supporting papers; correspondence; reports and briefs; cash books; grant applications and proposals; copies of the Association newsletter; and course outlines and teaching material.
The arrangement of the fonds into series is based on the Association's organizational structure. One series is reserved for records created by the central bodies, while each Division is assigned a separate series for divisional records transferred to the Archives. Within these groupings, the records were originally used and maintained by the Association or Division as a single unit of office files. Sub-series titles and arrangement have been supplied by the archivist in order to facilitate intellectual access to the documents. The arrangement was chosen to reflect activities falling under a similar function and generating related records. Nevertheless, overlap among groupings occurs, and the entire file list for the fonds should be reviewed to determine the existence of all files on a particular subject. Researchers should also be aware that strict chronological and alphabetical order was not originally maintained within files nor has it been supplied by the archivist. When the SFU Archives received the accrual of BCHPA records from the British Columbia Archives, some of the files related to other organizations, in particular, the British Columbia Commercial Beekeepers' Association. The archivist did not separate out these records because she did not know the circumstances of their acquisition and use by the BCPHA.
Bunse, Jacquie; Friedrich, Theo; Hardie, Blaine; Hanson, Sue; Heighway, C. C.; Feedham, W. C.; Hoadley, W. E.; Fuhr, Leo; Hart, S.; Turner, R.; Campkin, H.; Truscott, L.; Chandler, P.; Milot, E.; Lichtensteiger, D.; Lowing, Charlie; McGill, Ivan; Mahon, Hugh; Hanson, Dale; Fuhr, Rose; Bergenske, John; Pullein, Colin; Huxter, Terry; Hancock, Ted; Huxter, Elizabeth; Gibeau, John; Reist, Stan; Neidig, Wayne; Culley, Catherine; Clark, Kerry; Agriculture; Industries; Science and technology
All accessions have been processed as of August 2015. Further accruals are expected.
The records were in the custody of officers of the BCHPA prior to their transfer to Archives. The Central Executive and the various Divisions maintain separate records. The first accession was donated to the SFU Archives by the Association's Doug McCutcheon in February 2001. Approximately 1.25 metres of BCHPA records were previously acquired by the British Columbia Archives in 1987 from from John N. Robertson, then treasurer of BCHPA. The transfer of the material held by the BC Archives to the SFU Archives took place in 2003. Subsequent accessions were donated to the SFU Archives by the Association's John Boone (between 2007 and 2012) and Doug McCutcheon (in 2006, 2008, and 2011). A small accession was donated by Mark Winston in 2015.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the reference archivist for more details.
Copyright subsists in all or some of the records. Generally, the university is the copyright owner only to works that the donor authored. Please consult the reference archivist for details about the use of copyrighted materials.
- Association records, 1943 - 2005; F-147-1; 2.24 m of textual records 1 audio cassette
  published
  Series comprises records made or received by the Association's central organizations relating to Association-wide business. Activities documented include annual general meetings, meetings of the Central Executive and committees; revisions to the Association's constitution and organizational structure; financial management of Association funds; liaison with Divisions, government, and other organizations; production of the Association newsletter; development of educational initiatives; interventions in public-policy debates; participation in public fairs, markets and exhibits; and the administration of membership and the Boone Hodgson Wilkinson Trust Fund. For types of records, see sub-series descriptions.
  Series is arranged into 8 sub-series:
  1. Correspondence
  2. Financial records
  3. Meeting minutes
  4. Newsletters
  5. Organization records
  6. Projects and activities files
  7. Membership records
  8. Boone Hodgson Wilkinson Trust Fund records
  Files are arranged chronologically. As a result of an accrual added in 2014 (accessions 2012-001 and 2012-042), two additional sub-series were created by the processing archivist to facilitate intellectual access to the documents: F-147-1-7 (Membership records) and F-147-1-8 (Boone Hodgson Wilkinson Trust Fund records).
  Further accruals to the series are expected.
  - Correspondence, 1963 - 1998; F-147-1-1; 66 cm of textual records; Executive correspondence on meetings and topical issues can be found in some files originating from the 1990s and 2000s within the Meeting Minutes sub-series (F-147-1-3).
    Sub-series comprises correspondence conducted by Association officers with the Executive, members, Divisions, provincial and federal government ministries and agencies, and with other bee-related organizations and individuals. Records primarily include correspondence, but also include reports, newsletters, minutes, drafts, and other supporting documents.
    Textual records
    - Correspondence, 1980; F-147-1-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
      Pending review
    - Correspondence - pesticides, 1980 - 1981; F-147-1-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
    - Correspondence, 1981; F-147-1-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
    - Correspondence, 1982; F-147-1-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
    - Correspondence - Social Service Tax exemption, 1982; F-147-1-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
    - Correspondence - Bee Act interpretation, 1982 - 1983; F-147-1-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
    - Correspondence, 1983; F-147-1-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
    - Correspondence, 1984; F-147-1-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
    - Correspondence, 1985; F-147-1-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
    - Correspondence, 1986; F-147-1-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
    - Correspondence, 1987; F-147-1-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
    - Correspondence, 1988; F-147-1-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
    - Correspondence, 1989; F-147-1-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
    - Correspondence, 1992; F-147-1-1-0-14 (Archival box - standard 147-1)
    - Correspondence, 1993; F-147-1-1-0-15 (Archival box - standard 147-2)
    - Correspondence - Varroa mite, 1993; F-147-1-1-0-16 (Archival box - standard 147-2)
    - Correspondence, 1994; F-147-1-1-0-17 (Archival box - standard 147-2)
    - Correspondence, 1995; F-147-1-1-0-18 (Archival box - standard 147-2)
    - BCHPA: general correspondence, 1963 - 1969; F-147-1-1-0-19 (Archival box - standard 147-8)
    - BCHPA: general correspondence, 1970 - 1974; F-147-1-1-0-20 (Archival box - standard 147-8)
    - BCHPA: general correspondence, 1975 - 1976; F-147-1-1-0-21 (Archival box - standard 147-8)
    - BCHPA: general correspondence, 1976 - 1977; F-147-1-1-0-22 (Archival box - standard 147-8)
    - BCHPA: general correspondence, 1977 - 1978; F-147-1-1-0-23 (Archival box - standard 147-8)
    - BCHPA: general correspondence, 1978 - 1979; F-147-1-1-0-24 (Archival box - standard 147-8)
    - BCHPA: general correspondence, 1980; F-147-1-1-0-25 (Archival box - standard 147-8)
    - BCHPA: general correspondence, 1981 - 1984; F-147-1-1-0-26 (Archival box - standard 147-8)
    - BCHPA: divisions and general correspondence, 1976 - 1978; F-147-1-1-0-27 (Archival box - standard 147-9)
    - BCHPA: executive correspondence, 1977 - 1978; F-147-1-1-0-28 (Archival box - standard 147-9)
    - BCHPA: inward correspondence, 1973 - 1974; F-147-1-1-0-29 (Archival box - standard 147-9)
    - BCHPA: inward correspondence, 1974 - 1975; F-147-1-1-0-30 (Archival box - standard 147-9)
    - BCHPA: inward correspondence, 1975 - 1976; F-147-1-1-0-31 (Archival box - standard 147-10)
    - BCHPA: outward correspondence, 1973 - 1974; F-147-1-1-0-32 (Archival box - standard 147-10)
    - BCHPA: outward correspondence, 1974 - 1975; F-147-1-1-0-33 (Archival box - standard 147-10)
    - BCHPA: outward correspondence, 1975 - 1976; F-147-1-1-0-34 (Archival box - standard 147-10)
    - President's correspondence with Capital Region, vol. 1, 1991 - 1995; F-147-1-1-0-35 (Archival box - standard 147-19)
    - President's correspondence with Capital Region, vol. 2, 1991 - 1995; F-147-1-1-0-36 (Archival box - standard 147-19)
    - BCHPA correspondence, 1991 - 1998; F-147-1-1-0-37 (Archival box - standard 147-19)
    - Correspondence with Canadian Honey Council, vol. 1, 1993 - 1996; F-147-1-1-0-38 (Archival box - standard 147-19)
      Canadian Honey Council; Textual records
    - Correspondence with Canadian Honey Council, vol. 2, 1993 - 1996; F-147-1-1-0-39 (Archival box - standard 147-19)
    - Presidents' correspondence, reports and supporting documents, vol. 1, 1994 - 1998; F-147-1-1-0-40 (Archival box - standard 147-19)
    - Presidents' correspondence, reports and supporting documents, vol. 2, 1994 - 1998; F-147-1-1-0-41 (Archival box - standard 147-19)
    - Correspondence, 1994 - 1998; F-147-1-1-0-42 (Archival box - standard 147-20)
  - Financial records, 1955 - 1996; F-147-1-2; 9 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises records relating to the management of the BCHPA's financial resources. Activities documented include accounts management; grant proposals and applications; and some financial administration of the Association's Boone, Hodgson, Wilkinson Trust Fund, established in 1965 to support beekeeping research and education. Records consist of a cashbook from 1955, grant applications, correspondence and reports.
    Files are arranged chronologically, as are accrual additions.
    - Cash book, 1955; F-147-1-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 147-2)
    - Boone, Hodgson, Wilkinson trust fund, 1979 - 1983; F-147-1-2-0-2; Files pertaining to the BHW Trust Fund are also found in the Boone Hodgson Wilkinson Trust Fund Records sub-series (F-147-1-8). (Archival box - standard 147-2)
      Boone, Harvey; Hodgson, Percy; Wilkinson, George; Textual records
    - Lottery grant, 1988; F-147-1-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 147-2)
    - BCHPA: cash book, 1979 - 1983; F-147-1-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 147-10)
    - BCHPA: cash book, 1983 - 1984; F-147-1-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA: financial statements, 1962 - 1968; F-147-1-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA: journal no.1: general fund, 1975 - 1979; F-147-1-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA: journal no.2: good and welfare fund, 1975 - 1979; F-147-1-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA - financial, 1993 - 1996; F-147-1-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 147-20)
  - Meeting minutes, 1943 - 2005; F-147-1-3; 61 cm of textual records; Proceedings for the Association's annual meetings were bound for the years 1953-1977.
    Sub-series comprises minutes of meetings of the BCHPA, including Central Executive, annual general meetings and semi-annual meetings. Some files from the 1990s and 2000s also include inward and outward Executive correspondence on meetings and topical issues, as well as "Executive Doings," a circular sent to Divisions and affiliates. Records consist of minutes, resolutions, programs, correspondence, reports, and meeting support papers.
    Files are arranged chronologically.
    - Annual meetings, 1947 - 1952; F-147-1-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 147-2)
    - Annual meetings, 1953 - 1967; F-147-1-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 147-2)
    - Annual meetings, 1954 - 1959; F-147-1-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 147-2)
    - Annual meetings, 1967 - 1970; F-147-1-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 147-2)
    - Annual meetings, 1968 - 1977; F-147-1-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 147-3)
    - Semi-annual meeting, 1974; F-147-1-3-0-6 (Archival box - standard 147-3)
    - Executive and annual general meeting, 1978; F-147-1-3-0-7 (Archival box - standard 147-3)
    - Annual general meeting, 1979; F-147-1-3-0-8 (Archival box - standard 147-3)
    - Semi-annual and annual meetings, 1980; F-147-1-3-0-9 (Archival box - standard 147-3)
    - Semi-annual and annual meetings, 1981; F-147-1-3-0-10 (Archival box - standard 147-3)
    - Semi-annual and annual meetings, 1982; F-147-1-3-0-11 (Archival box - standard 147-3)
    - Semi-annual and annual meetings, 1983; F-147-1-3-0-12 (Archival box - standard 147-3)
    - Annual general meeting, 1984; F-147-1-3-0-13 (Archival box - standard 147-3)
    - Resolutions, 1984 - 1987; F-147-1-3-0-14 (Archival box - standard 147-3)
    - Executive Board, semi-annual, and annual meetings, 1985; F-147-1-3-0-15 (Archival box - standard 147-3)
    - Executive Board, semi-annual, and annual meetings, 1986; F-147-1-3-0-16 (Archival box - standard 147-3)
    - Executive Board, semi-annual, and annual meetings, 1987; F-147-1-3-0-17 (Archival box - standard 147-4)
    - Executive Board, semi-annual and general meetings, 1988; F-147-1-3-0-18 (Archival box - standard 147-4)
    - Executive Board, semi-annual, and annual meetings, 1989; F-147-1-3-0-19 (Archival box - standard 147-4)
    - Semi-annual and annual general meetings, 1990; F-147-1-3-0-20 (Archival box - standard 147-4)
    - Executive Board, semi-annual, and annual meetings, 1991; F-147-1-3-0-21 (Archival box - standard 147-4)
    - Executive Committee, semi-annual and annual general meetings, 1992; F-147-1-3-0-22 (Archival box - standard 147-4)
    - Executive Committee, semi-annual and annual general meetings, 1993; F-147-1-3-0-23 (Archival box - standard 147-4)
    - Executive Board, semi-annual, and annual meetings, 1994; F-147-1-3-0-24 (Archival box - standard 147-4)
    - Executive Board, semi-annual, and annual meetings, 1995; F-147-1-3-0-25 (Archival box - standard 147-4)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 23rd - Vernon, 1943; F-147-1-3-0-26 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 24th - Vernon, 1944; F-147-1-3-0-27 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 28th - Vancouver, 1947; F-147-1-3-0-28 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 29th - Kamloops, 1948; F-147-1-3-0-29 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 30th - Salmon Arm, 1949; F-147-1-3-0-30 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 31st - Summerland, 1950; F-147-1-3-0-31 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 32nd - New Westminster, 1951; F-147-1-3-0-32 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 33rd - Oliver, 1952; F-147-1-3-0-33 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 34th - Salmon Arm, 1953; F-147-1-3-0-34 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 35th - Vernon, 1954; F-147-1-3-0-35 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 36th - Kelowna, 1955; F-147-1-3-0-36 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 37th - Kamloops, 1956; F-147-1-3-0-37 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 38th - Vancouver, 1956; F-147-1-3-0-38 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 39th - Salmon Arm, 1957; F-147-1-3-0-39 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 40th - Milner, 1958; F-147-1-3-0-40 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 42nd - Mission, 1960; F-147-1-3-0-41 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 43rd - Vernon, 1961; F-147-1-3-0-42 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 44th - Victoria, 1962; F-147-1-3-0-43 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 45th - Kamloops, 1963; F-147-1-3-0-44 (Archival box - standard 147-11)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 46th - Mission, 1964; F-147-1-3-0-45 (Archival box - standard 147-12)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 47th - Salmon Arm, 1965; F-147-1-3-0-46 (Archival box - standard 147-12)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 48th - Creston, 1966; F-147-1-3-0-47 (Archival box - standard 147-12)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 50th - New Westminster, 1968; F-147-1-3-0-48 (Archival box - standard 147-12)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 51st - Salem, Oregon, 1969; F-147-1-3-0-49 (Archival box - standard 147-12)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 60th - Victoria, 1978; F-147-1-3-0-50 (Archival box - standard 147-12)
    - BCHPA AGM of Central Executive: 63rd - Comox, 1981; F-147-1-3-0-51 (Archival box - standard 147-12)
    - BCHPA semi-annual meeting of Central Executive - Surrey, 1974 - 1974; F-147-1-3-0-52 (Archival box - standard 147-12)
    - BCHPA semi-annual meeting of Central Executive - Kamloops, 1979 - 1979; F-147-1-3-0-53 (Archival box - standard 147-12)
    - Semi-annual meeting minutes and Honeybee Nucleus Studies (D.A.T.E. Project 329) summary report, 1991; F-147-1-3-0-54 (Archival box - standard 147-20)
    - AGM - Victoria, Executive Committee minutes, President's report, and supporting documentation, 1991; F-147-1-3-0-55 (Archival box - standard 147-20)
    - SAGM, Executive Committee minutes, and correspondence on various issues, 1992; F-147-1-3-0-56 (Archival box - standard 147-20)
    - AGM - Aldergrove and Executive Committee minutes, 1992; F-147-1-3-0-57 (Archival box - standard 147-20)
    - SAGM, Executive Committee minutes, Executive Doings, and correspondence, 1993; F-147-1-3-0-58 (Archival box - standard 147-20)
    - AGM - Prince George, Executive Committee minutes, and Executive Doings, 1993; F-147-1-3-0-59 (Archival box - standard 147-20)
    - SAGM and AGM, Executive Committee minutes, briefings, and correspondence on various issues, 1994; F-147-1-3-0-60 (Archival box - standard 147-20)
    - AGM - Duncan, SAGM, Executive Committee minutes, Executive Doings, and correspondence on various issues, 1995; F-147-1-3-0-61 (Archival box - standard 147-20)
    - AGM and SAGM, Executive Committee minutes, and Executive Doings, 1996; F-147-1-3-0-62 (Archival box - standard 147-20)
    - SAGM, AGM, Executive Committee minutes, Executive Doings, and correspondence on various issues, 1997; F-147-1-3-0-63 (Archival box - standard 147-20)
    - BCHPA Central Executive teleconference minutes, supporting documents, and correspondence on various issues, [ca. 1997] - 2005; F-147-1-3-0-64 (Archival box - standard 147-20)
    - SAGM, AGM, and Executive Doings, 1998; F-147-1-3-0-65 (Archival box - standard 147-21)
    - Semi-annual and annual general meetings, 1999; F-147-1-3-0-66 (Archival box - standard 147-21)
    - Semi-annual and annual general meeting minutes, 2000; F-147-1-3-0-67 (Archival box - standard 147-21)
    - Semi-annual general meeting minutes and financial balance sheet, 2001; F-147-1-3-0-68 (Archival box - standard 147-21)
    - SAGM minutes and AGM Educational Day notes, 2002; F-147-1-3-0-69 (Archival box - standard 147-21)
    - Semi-annual and annual general meeting minutes, 2003; F-147-1-3-0-70 (Archival box - standard 147-21)
    - Semi-annual and annual general meeting minutes, President's report, 2004; F-147-1-3-0-71 (Archival box - standard 147-21)
    - Semi-annual and annual general meeting minutes, 2005; F-147-1-3-0-72 (Archival box - standard 147-21)
  - Newsletters, 1968 - 2005; F-147-1-4; 28.5 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises copies of the Association's newsletter. In 1968 one issue appeared, called Bee Cee Bees. There is a gap in the series until 1979, by which time the newsletter was appearing quarterly, edited by Allan King, and called simply the BCHPA Newsletter. In 1985 the newsletter was re-launched as a new quarterly publication under the name BeeScene. It continues to be published in this form.